Register of the Polish Subject Collection, 1918-2014
Hoover Institution Archives
Polish Subject collection,
1918-2014
XX747
Hoover Institution Archives
104 manuscript boxes, 11 oversize boxes, 2 oversize folders, 2 cubic foot boxes, 1 microfilm reel, 36 compact cassette tapes, 15 video cassette tapes, memorabilia, (59.3 linear feet)
Serial issues, pamphlets, election campaign literature, proclamations, other printed matter, correspondence, reports, and miscellany relating to various aspects of Polish history, including the movement for independence, especially during World War I; the Solidarność trade union movement; and political events and elections since 1989. Includes clandestine anti-communist issuances from World War II and the early post-war period.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Collection note
Materials in the Polish Subject collection have been collected over time by the Hoover Institution Library and Archives from various creators and are reflective of Polish history from 1918 to 2014.
Noteworthy parts of this collection are materials attributed to Władysław Chojnacki, a distinguished Polish historian, bibliographer, and scholar.
NSZZ "Solidarność" (Labor organization); Anti-communist movements--Poland.; Communism.; Elections--Poland.; Labor movement--Poland.; Phonotapes.; Poland--History--20th century.; Poland--Politics and government--1980-1989.; Poland--Politics and government--1989-; Poland.; Trade-unions--Poland.; Video tapes.; World War, 1914-1918--Poland.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1791-1995 (Boxes 1-34)
  General note
  Correspondence, mimeographs, typescripts, catalogs, bulletins, bibliographic publications, flyers, leaflets, pamphlets, clippings, press releases, newspaper issues, posters, and miscellany printed material, arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by subject
  - Constitution. Fascimile of original English translation published in London in 1791 (Text 1)
  - Socialist movements, 1864-1918
  - 20th century. Okhrana. English translations of office correspondence and instructions, 1908
  - Revolution of, 1905
    - General
    - Calls for strikes
  - World War I, 1914-1918
    - Austrian occupation, 1915-1918
      - Pilsudzki, Jozef
      - Polish Legions
    - German occupation, 1914-1918
      - General
      - German soldiers, Appeals to
      - Polish military formations
      - General
      - Sikorski, Wladyslaw. Speech on voluntary enlistment, 1917
    - Russian occupation. Jewish problem
  - 1918
    - General
    - Army
      - General
      - Polska Organizacja Wojskowa
      - Wojsko Polskie
    - Labor unions, workers associations. Includes communist anti-state agitation
      - General
      - Narodowy Zwiazek Robotniczy
      - Rady Delegatow Robotniczych
        - General
        - Warszawa
        - Zaglebie Dabrowskie i Sosnowiec
      - Zwiazek Robotnikow Miejskich s.m. Warszawy
      - Zwiazek Zawodowy Robotnikow Rolnych
    - Organizations
      - Ethnic-Jewish
        - General
          - General
          - Publications
            - Yiddish
            - Polish
        - Bund
      - Political-Nationalist, pre-independence
        - Centralny Demokratyczny Komitet Wyborczy
        - Klub Panstwowcow Polskich
        - Konfederacja Narodowa
        - Liga Panstwowosci Polskiej
        - Miedzypartyjne Kolo Polityczne
        - Zjednoczenie Narodowe
        - Zwiazek Budowy Panstwa Polskiego
      - Youth
      - Women
    - Political parties. Includes some material from, 1917 (Text 2)
      - General
      - Anarchists
      - Komunistyczna Partia Robotnicza Polski
      - Narodowy Zwiazek Robotniczy
      - Polska Partia Socjalistyczna
      - Polskie Stronnictwo Ludowe
      - Polskie Zjednoczenie Ludowe
      - Socjaldemokracja Krolestwa Polskiego i Litwy
        - General
          - Hebrew publications: "Zum Kampf", "Die Kontrrevolutionare Rolle", 1918
          - Pamphlets
        - Committees
          - Lithuania
          - Southern Poland
          - Warsaw
        - Zarzad Glowny
      - Stronnictwo Niezawislosci Narodowej
      - Zjednoczone Stronnictwa Niepodleglosciowe
      - Zjednoczenie Stronnictw Demokratycznych
      - Zwiazek Demokracji Polskiej
    - Pretender to Polish throne, Archduke Karol Stefan
    - Provisional government. Rada Stanu Krolestwa Polskiego
  - Wars of, 1918-1921 (Text 3)
    - Polish-Soviet war, 1920-1921
    - "K.B.P. Referat Prasowy. Referat z prasy polskiej w sprawie kresow wschodnich, od 1-go do 15-go czerwca r.", 1920
    - Leaflets
      - Polish. Addressed to
        - Polish soldiers
        - Soviet soldiers
      - Russian
    - Proclamations, Polish
    - Rady Zolnierskie
    - Territorial questions
  - 1918-1945
    - General. Patriotic flyers relating to May 3 celebrations, death of Marshall Jozef Pilsudzki, religious holidays, 1930-1939
    - Elections. Sejm Ustawodawczy (Constituent Assembly), Original copies of ballots, 1919 January.
    - Plebiscites, 1919
      - East Prussia
      - Spiz and Orawa
      - Teschen Silesia
      - Upper Silesia. Maps on coal production and appeals to Polish workers
    - Political conditions (Text 4)
      - General
      - Political parties
        - Komunistyczna Partia Gornego Slaska
        - Komunistyczna Partia Robotnicza Polski
          - General
          - Komitet Centralny
          - Komitet Organizujacy
          - Komitet Warszawski
          - Komitety lokalne
        - Polska Partia Socjalistyczna
          - General
            - General
            - Centralny Komitet Robotniczy
            - Rada Naczelna
            - Warszawski Komitet Robotniczy
          - Polska Partia Socjalistyczna-Lewica
            - Komitety Prowincjonalne
            - Komitet Robotniczy
            - Warszawski Komitet Robotniczy
          - Polska Partia Socjalistyczna Opozycja
        - Polska Partia Socyalno-Demokratyczna
        - Socjaldemokracja Krolestwa Polskiego i Litwy i Polska Partia Socjalistyczna-Lewica
  - Coup d'etat, 1926
    - General
    - Reports
  - Occupation, 1939-1945
    - Government in Exile
      - General
      - Publications (Text 5)
        - "Digest of Polish press, September 1943"
        - "Przeglad prasy podziemnej, zerwiec-sierpien, Government quarterly bulletin. Issue devoted mostly to death of General Wladyslaw Sikorski, 1943".
      - Memorandum of Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs to Foreign Ministers Summit in, 1959
      - Pamphlets
        - Army
        - Borders
        - British Commonwealth
        - Central European Federation
        - Culture
        - Economics
        - Foreign relations
        - Germany
        - Government, Policies of
        - History
        - Legal system
        - Minorities
        - Poles abroad
        - Political satire
        - Post-war programs
        - Regions of Poland and border conflicts (Text 6)
        - Religion and Vatican's policy toward Poland
        - Social issues
        - Youth
        - World War II developments
    - Katyn Forest massacre. Polish Air Force Veterans Association. "Katyn Memorial 1940-1990". Publication on 50th anniversary of Katyn. In Polish
    - Mausoleum of Struggle and Martyrdom, Warsaw Aleja Szucha. Brochure
  - 1945-
    - Emigre publications
      - Catholicism
        - Catholic Poland, by Alexander Tomsky, 1982
        - Idee spoleczne encykliki: Mater et magistra, by Jan Sliwa, n.d.
        - Encyklika o nowych zagadnieniach spolecznych: Mater et magistra, by Pope John XXIII, 1961
        - Stolica sw. w obronie praw polskich katolikow, w Rzeszy i w Polsce pod okupacja niemiecka, n.a., 1946
        - The Millenium of Poland, by P. Siekanowicz, 1966
      - Communist Poland
        - Amnestia: Dokumenty i objasnienia, n.a., 1956
        - For the Freedom of Poland and Central-Eastern Europe: Documents 1946-1947, by Council of Polish Political Parties, 1948
        - Forced Labor and Confinement without Trial in Poland, by Stafan Rosada, Jozef Gwozdz, 1952
        - Freedom of the Press in Poland, by M. E. Rojek, 1946
        - Ideologiczne troski komunistow w swietle XIII plenum Komitetu Centralnego PZPR, by Stefan Mekarski, 1963
        - Poland 1964: A Study in Lost Hopes, by Jerzy Lozowski, (?), 1965
        - Poland Today as Seen by Foreign Observers, ed. by M. K. Dziewanowski, 1946
        - Polish Elections: The Background, by Duchess of Atholl, 1947
        - The Polish Elections, 19th January, 1947, by British Joint Committee for Polish Affairs
        - Soviet-Polish Relations: A Collection of Official Documents and Press Extracts, 1944-1946, by Soviet News
        - Struggle for Democracy in Poland, by L. Stachow, 1979
        - La Verita ai Lavoratori, by Wladyslaw Gomulka, 1956
        - Who's Who of the Regime in Poland, by Scottish League for European Freedom, 1947
      - Culture and ideology (Text 7)
        - Jednostka w ustroju sowieckim, by Mateusz Skiba, 1948
        - Kalendarz Dziennika Polskiego na rok panski 1950
        - Marksizm w swietle nauki i faktow, by Leon Kownacki, 1954
        - O Freudzie i Einsteinie jako oszustach w nauce, by Z. J. Daszewski, 1955
        - Przewrot obcy w kulturze polskiej, by Stefan Mekarski, 1952
        - Trzy ksiazki G. Orwella, Cz. Milosza, W. Gombrowicza, by Z. Daszewski, 1954
      - Eastern Europe
        - Is this the New Europe, by Stanislaw Stronski, n.d.
        - Kryzys emigracji: Problemy federacji srodkowo-wschodniej Europy, by Stanislaw Olszewski, 1955
        - The Soviet Conquest in Central and Eastern Europe, by Stefan Lochtin, 1954
      - Events of 1956. Narod Polski w walce o wolnosc i niepodleglosc, 1956-1957, by Stanislaw Mikolajczyk
      - Government and politics in exile
        - Akt zjednoczenia, by Jan Kord, 1954
        - British-Polish Alliance, Its Origin and Meaning, by Edward Raczynski, 1948
        - Dzieje grzechu czyli od Jalty do przesilenia, by Adam Pragier, 1947
        - Kryzys prezydencki i droga wyjscia, by Zdzislaw Stahl, 1954
        - Od kleski do nadziei, w trzechlecie powstania Skarbu Narodowego, by Wieslaw Wohnout, 1953
        - Polski rzad na wygnaniu i jego misja, by Tomasz Kolakowski, n.d.
      - Organization of Captive Nations, 1955
        - Nadzwyczjana sesja Organizacji Narodow Ujarzmionych Europy a Strasburgu od 1 do 5 lipca 1955, report by Polski Narodowy Komitet Demokratyczny
        - Estonia. Map of Estonian liberation war, New York, 1919, 1939
      - Poles abroad
        - Kraj i emigracja, by Wojciech Laryssa, 1947
        - Polska emigracja polityczna po 20 latach: Jej alternatywy i przyszlosc, by Jerzy Hauptman, 1965
        - Poradnik prawny dla Polakow w Niemczech: Legal Aid Manual for Poles in Germany, 1952
        - Sprawozdanie z dzialalnosci Funduszu Pomocy Polakom za okres od 1943 do marca 1961, by Fundusz Pomocy Polakom
      - Polish history
        - Bez Boga, honoru, ojczyzny: Ostatnie dni II Marszalka Polski i min. J. Becka (z raportow dyplomatow), by Witold Benedykt Kuk, 1953
        - Konstytucja 3 maja 1791 na tle porownawczym, by Waclaw Komarnicki, 1951
        - Polska w pamietnikach gen. de Gaulle'a. Wybor tekstow z przedmowa Kajetana Morawskiego, by Kajetan Morawski
        - Szymon Budny: Der groesste Haeretiker Litauens im 16. Jahrhundert, by Stanislaw Kot, 1956
      - Political parties abroad
        - Cel i droga: Dwa dokumenty: 1. Deklaracja: Cele i zadania PPS, 2. Alternatywa Socjalistyczna w krajach Srodkowo - Wschodniej Europy, by Zygmunt Zaremba, 1963
        - Demokratyczne ustroje panstwowe, by Leon Kownacki, 1952
        - Polish National Democratic Committee, Third Session, 1955, by Polish National Democratic Committee
        - Polityka Polskiej Demokracji: III kongres Polskiego Stronnictwa Ludowego we Francji w dniach 24-25 lutego 1952, n.a.
        - Polskie stronnictwa i ich doktryny, by Testis, 1953
        - Przeciw zdradzie socjalizmu i demokracji: P.P.S., by Henryk Polowiec, 1954
        - To sie dawno zaczelo: Stronnictwo Ludowe, by Wojciech Piechota, 1948
        - Wytyczne polityki Polskiej Demokracji na wygnaniu: Druga sesja Polskiego Narodowego Komitetu Demokratycznego, n.a., 1953
      - Post-war western border
        - Bronmy granicy na Odrze i Nysie, by Marian Seyda, 1948
        - Hopes and Fears of German Unification, by Jerzy Hauptman, 1965
        - Najwazniejsza dzis dla Polakow sprawa, by Komitet Obrony Zachodnich Kresow Polski, 1947
        - Sprawa granicy zachodniej to dla Polakow byc albo nie byc, by Leon T. Walkowicz, 1947
        - Zagadnienia gospodarcze ziem odzyskanych, by Zbigniew M. Fallenbuchl, 1956
      - Pre-war politics. Idea niepodleglosci i sily u Jozefa Pilsudzkiego, by Zdzislaw Stahl, 1952
  - 1945-1980 (Text 8)
    - Censorship. "Noty Biograficzne". Biographical dictionary of Polish emigres published by Central Press Office, Publications and Performance Controll, 1971
    - Communist party, Formation and apparatus of
      - General. Pamphlets. In Polish
        - General
          - General
          - Formation of party apparatus
        - Army propaganda
        - Culture and education
        - Economy
        - Educational system
        - History. World War I, interwar period, 1914-1918
        - Legal and political system
        - Opposition, as viewed by party ideologues. Includes material on Kultura (Paris), Polish emigre circles
        - Peasant political movement (Text 9)
        - Territories regained after World War II
        - Youth movement
        - World War II, 1939-1945
      - Unification congress, autograph book of attendees, 1948 December.
    - Concentration camp prisoners, Testimonies of former. Polski Instytut Zrodlowy w Lund in Polish and English, 1945-1946.
    - Spain - History - Civil War, Poles, former participants as prisoners of war in France, Germany, Spain, 1936-1939. 1939-1945
    - "Zwiazek Patriotow Polskich. Biuletyn Zarzadu Obwodowego ZPP w Molotowie. Polak na Uralu" No., 1, 1945 November
  - Uprising, 1956 (Text 10)
    - Articles
      - Khrushchev, Nikita. Interview for CBS in Polish, 1957 May 28.
      - Stalin, Joseph. Obituary issue of Express Wieczorny, in Polish, 1953 March 9.
      - Newspapers issues relating to political situation and dialogue
        - Glos Koszalinski
        - Glos Szczecinski
        - Nowa Kultura
        - Po Prostu
        - Przeglad Kulturalny
        - Swiat
        - Trybuna Ludu
        - Ziemia i Morze
        - Zycie Literackie
  - 1956-1980
    - Elections, Voting ballot for Sejm with Wojciech Jaruzelski leading list of candidates, 1976.
    - Gierek, Edward, speech delivered to shipyard workers in (?), 1980
    - Political opposition, 1976-1980
      - General
        - Catholic groups. Includes material on John Paul II visit to Poland and official releases of episcopate, 1979
        - Peasant organizations (Text 11)
        - Student organizations. Includes material on position of official government organizations
      - Komitet Obrony Robotnikow
        - 1977
        - 1978
        - 1979
          - January-June
          - July-December
        - 1980 (Text 12)
          - January-June
          - July
          - August
            - General
            - Communist party, Official literature on
            - Strike folklore. Poems and ballads. Includes material from later period
      - Komitet Porozumienia na Rzecz Samostanowienia Narodu, 1980
      - Konfederacja Polski Niepodleglej, 1978-1980
      - N.S.Z.Z. Solidarnosc
        - 1980
          - General
            - General
            - Flyers
          - August
            - Gdansk region
            - Warsaw region
          - September
          - October
          - November (Text 13)
          - December
      - Ruch Obrony Praw Czlowieka i Obywatela, 1978-1980
      - Ruch Wolnych Demokratow, 1978-1980
  - 1980-1989 (Text 14)
    - General. Calendars commemorating XX century events and historic figures
    - Communist party
      - Central Committee. "Przyczyny, przebieg i skutki kryzysow spolecznych w dziejach PRL", (?). Political analysis on causes of social unrests in post-war communist Poland. Copy of typescript, 1982
      - Propaganda
        - Political pamphlets, 1982-1987
          - Catholic church
          - Foreign relations
          - Internal developments
          - Official party program
          - Opposition, Internal and foreign
        - Press review bulletins. In Polish and English, 1981 February-April.
    - Individuals
      - Matejko, Alexander. Curriculum vitae and list of publications, 1971
      - Milosz, Czeslaw. Speech delivered at Nobel Prize Ceremony
      - Popieluszko, Jerzy
      - Pruszynski, Aleksander. Correspondence with
        - Stefan Bratkowski, Jan Rulewski, Danuta and Lech Walesa, Roman Zambrowski, 1981-1989
      - Vysotskii, Vladimir. Transcript of his performance in Poland, March 1981
    - NSZZ Solidarnosc (Text 15)
      - Bibliographies of underground publications. General
        - "Katalog prasy podziemnej w Bibliotece Polskiej w Paryzu", n.d.
        - "Katalog zawartosci polskiej prasy niezaleznej: Contents of the Polish underground press" by Kontakt, 1986
          - Part I
          - Part II
        - NSZZ Solidarnosc collection. University of Toronto. Thomas Fisher Rare Book Library
          - General. General guide
          - Finding aids. Period files
            - Martial law
            - Post-martial law
            - Pre-solidarity
            - Solidarity legal
          - Indices (Text 16)
            - General, alphabetical
            - Independent publishers
            - Uncensored books
            - Uncensored periodicals
        - "Polish Independent Publications 1976+", Solidarity Bibliographic Center, Harvard University
      - Office issuances. Contains some material of other opposition groups and associations related ideologically to Solidarity
        - 1981
          - General
            - January
            - February (Text 17)
            - March
            - April
            - May
            - June
            - July
            - August
            - September
            - October
            - November
            - December
          - Komisja Zakladowa Kombinatu Dzwigow Osobowych "Zreb", Warszawa. Protocols (Text 18)
            - 1980-1981
            - 1982
            - 1983
            - 1984
              - General
              - 10x
            - 1985
            - 1986
            - 1987 (Text 19)
            - 1988
      - Memoirs. Authors unknown, n.d.
      - Publications, 1985-1986
      - Representatives abroad file, 1980-1989 (Text 20)
        - General
        - Australia
        - Austria
        - Belgium
        - Canada
        - France
        - Germany
        - Great Britain
        - Greece
        - Italy
        - Japan
        - Norway (Text 21)
        - Sweden
        - United States
    - Pomaranczowa Alternatywa, 1987-1988 (Text 22)
    - Round table talks, 1989 February 6 -April 5
      - General
      - "Komitet organizacyjny przy Lechu Walesie d.s. Okraglego stolu", nos. 38-40
      - "Okragly stol. Kto jest kim. Opozycja", 1989
      - "Porozumienia okraglego stolu". Final report
    - Solidarnosc Walczaca, Kornel Morawiecki, 1987-1988
    - Zwiazek Literatow Polskich. Directory, 1981
  - 1989-1993 (Text 23)
    - American Studies Center in Warsaw, 1991-1992
    - Constitution. Programs of various political groups, 1990-1993
    - Economic reform
      - General. Business periodicals, 1990-1993
      - Centrum Adama Smitha. Statute
      - Fundacja Rataja. Pamphlets
    - Elections
      - Municipal, 1994 June 19
      - Parliamentary
        - Posters and flyers, 1989.
        - 1991 October
          - General
            - General
            - Labor unions
            - Left oriented groups
            - Minorities (Text 24)
            - Tygodnik Wyborczy, August-October
          - Konfederacja Polski Niepodleglej
          - Kongres Liberalno Demokratyczny
          - Partia Konserwatywno Liberalna
          - Partia Wolnosci
          - Partia X
          - Polska Wspolnota Narodowa
          - Polskie Stronnictwo Ludowe
          - Porozumienie Ludowe
          - Porozumienie Obywatelskie Centrum
            - General
            - "Serwis Informacyjny"
          - Sojusz Lewicy Demokratycznej
          - Solidarnosc and Solidarnosc Pracy
          - Stronnictwo Demokratyczne
          - Stronnictwo Sprawiedliwosci Spolecznej
          - Unia Demokratyczna
          - Unia Polityki Realnej
          - Victoria, Polaczone Sztaby Wyborcze Lecha Walesy
          - Zjednoczenie Chrzescijansko Narodowe
        - 1993 (Text 25)
          - General
            - General
            - Merkuriusz partii i ugrupowan politycznych, nos., 1-15, 1993
          - Bezpartyjny Blok Wspierania Reform
          - Katolicki Komitet Wyborczy "Ojczyzna" Koalicja dla Rzeczpospolitej
            - General
            - Partia Wolnosci
            - Political program
          - Klub Zachowawczo Monarchistyczny
          - Konfederacja Polski Niepodleglej
          - Kongres Liberalno-Demokratyczny
            - General
            - Program
          - Niezalezny Samorzadny Zwiazek Zawodowy "Solidarnosc" (Text 26)
          - Polskie Stronnictwo Ludowe
          - Porozumienie Centrum. Zjednoczenie Polskie
          - Samoobrona
          - Sojusz Lewicy Demokratycznej (Text 27)
            - General
            - Demokratyczna Unia Kobiet
          - Stronnictwo Sprawiedliwosci Spolecznej
          - Unia Demokratyczna
            - Lists of candidates
            - Political program
          - Unia Polityki Realnej
          - Unia Pracy
          - Wspolnota Narodowa
          - Zjednoczenie Chrzescijansko Narodowe
      - Presidential
        - 1990
          - Bartoszcze, Roman
          - Cimoszewicz, Wlodzimierz
          - Mazowiecki, Tadeusz
          - Tyminski, Stanislaw
          - Walesa, Lech
        - 1995 (Text 39)
          - Gronkiewicz-Waltz, Hanna
          - Kwasniewski, Aleksander
          - Kuron, Jacek
          - Moczulski, Leszek
          - Walesa, Lech
    - Green card lottery. Flyer distributed in Poland, 1992 (Text 28)
    - McDonald, Warsaw
    - NSZZ Solidarnosc
      - General, 1989-1992
      - Rada Krajowa
        - General. Biuletyn Informacyjny, 1990-1993
        - Office issuances, resolutions, 1989-1992
      - Solidarnosc Rolnicza, 1989-1992
    - Political parties, 1990-1994 (Text 29)
      - General
        - General
        - Guides, 1991
      - Forum Pro-Amerykanskie (Unia Amerykansko-Polska)
      - Konfederacja Polski Niepodleglej
        - General
        - Political program
          - General. Pamphlets
          - Biuletyn Informacyjny, 1992-1993 (Text 30)
          - Gazeta Polska, 1992-1993
          - Prasa o KPN
            - 1992
            - 1993 (Text 31)
      - Kongres Liberalno Demokratyczny
        - Bulletins
        - Program
      - Niezalezny Samorzadny Zwiazek Zawodowy "Solidarnosc"